Preliminary Guide to the Alexander Maclaren Witherspoon Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alexander Maclaren Witherspoon papers
1916-1964
MS 528
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
31
Lectures, notes, subject files, exams, and correspondence from Witherspoon's teaching career at Yale University. Also included are correspondence and manuscripts of Albert Hampton Barclay.
Witherspoon, Alexander M. (Alexander Maclaren), 1894-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles A. Walker, 1969.
Conditions Governing Access
Gradebooks in Box 31 are restricted until January 1, 2024 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Biographical / Historical
Alexander M. Witherspoon (1894-1964): Educator; B.A., Yale, 1918, M.A., 1921, Ph.D., 1923; instructor in English, Yale, 1923-1926, assistant professor, 1926-1935, associate professor, 1935-1963, professor emeritus, 1963-1964.
He was the author of The Influence of Robert Garnier on Elizabethan Drama (Yale Press, 1924) and Common Errors in English (Doubleday, Doran, 1943) and he was the editor of Titus Andronicus in the Yale Shakespeare Series (Yale Press, 1926) and the co-editor of Seventeenth-Century Prose and Poetry (1929, 1946) and The College Survey of English Literature (1942, 1952), both published by Harcourt, Brace. Since 1953 Witherspoon has been on the editorial board of The Complete Prose Works of John Milton (eight volume—Yale Press, 1953—), and he was co-editor of Volume Four of the series, published in 1953. He was also a member of the editorial board of the Masterworks Series (five volumes—Doubleday, Doran, 1946-50). He belonged to the Modern Language Association of America, the Modern Humanities Research Association, the National Council of Teachers of English, the American Association of University Professors (secretary-treasurer of the Yale chapter, 1940-44), the Elizabethan Club (formerly president), the Graduates Club, "The Club" of New Haven, and United Church. He was unmarried.
History of the Class of 1918 Yale College, Forty Years On. Vol. II (1954), pp. 371-372.
Scope and Contents
Lectures, notes, subject files, exams, and correspondence from Witherspoon's teaching career at Yale University. Also included are correspondence and manuscripts of Albert Hampton Barclay.
English literature -- Study and teaching; Literature -- History and criticism; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Educators; Barclay, Albert Hampton, 1869-1951; Witherspoon, Alexander M. (Alexander Maclaren), 1894-1964; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  These papers are poorly organized; this listing attempts only to make retrieval possible. All dates are approximate. It is not clear why Witherspoon should have had some papers of Albert Hampton Barclay (1869-1951; Y. 1891). The greater part of the papers consists of "collateral notes," which was Witherspoon's term for his subject files.
  - Lectures: notes, typescripts, student papers, course materials, printed matter., 1934-1948 (Box 1)
  - Bible class: notes, printed matter, 1934-1943, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - The College Survey of English Literature: volumes, with AMW's annotations, notes, and printed matter. One volume in Box 4, 1942-1948 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: typescripts, printed matter, some correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 2)
  - "Collateral notes" (hereafter CN): lecture and research materials on various writers and subjects: notes, printed matter, some typescripts and student papers. Materials are sorted into manila envelopes, but envelopes are not in any order, 1930-1959 (Box 3–5)
  - CN on Milton, 1916-1919 (Box 6)
  - CN on Thomas Browne, 1955-1959 (Box 6)
  - CN, including drawings by a student (Box 7)
  - Note cards, undated (Box 7–8)
  - Comprehensive Study Group: stencils, undated (Box 8)
  - Departmental papers (Box 8)
  - Exams, course hand-outs, miscellaneous, 1938-1963 (Box 8)
  - Exams (suggested questions), miscellaneous, 1945-1959 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, some re: Complete Prose Works of John Milton, 1948-1963 (Box 9)
  - CN (Box 10)
  - Exams, 1953-1960 (Box 10)
  - Note cards, undated (Box 10)
  - CN (Dryden and others), including stencils (Box 11)
  - Albert Hampton Barclay: correspondence, MSS, printed matter, 1916-1938 (Box 12–13)
  - CN (Box 13)
  - Photographs (framed), 1944, undated (Box 13)
  - Glass ball containing metal dog, undated (Box 13)
  - CN (Box 14)
  - CN on Milton (Box 15)
  - Printed map, 1931 (Box 15)
  - CN (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1929 (Box 16)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, mostly weather records, 1938-1958 (Box 16)
  - CN (Box 17)
  - Exams, 1958-1961 (Box 17)
  - Milton Fund: correspondence and financial statements, 1952-1963 (Box 17)
  - Scrapbook of clippings on Milton, 1928-1937 (Box 17)
  - Exams: Freshman English, 1917-1940 (Box 18)
  - CN, especially on Milton and Shakespeare (Box 18–19)
  - CN (Box 20)
  - Exams, 1918-1935 (Box 20)
  - The College Survey of English Literature: critical correspondence, 1942-1948 (Box 20)
  - CN (Box 21–25)
  - Stencils, undated (Box 25)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 25)
  - Notebooks kept by AMW as a student, undated (Box 26)
  - Textbooks (Box 26)
  - Stencils, undated (Box 26)
  - Printed matter (Box 26)
  - Exam booklets (blank, or used as notebooks), 1957-1961 (Box 27)
  - Stencils, undated (Box 27)
  - Financial records, 1963-1964 (Box 27)
  - Death announcements and materials re: memorial service, 1964 (Box 27)
  - CN (Box 27–29)
  - Note cards, undated (Box 29)
  - CN (Box 30–31)
  - Grade books, 1939-1942, 1949 (Box 31)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Grade books are closed until January 1, 2024 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.